<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Christs Church in Dublin, Jan. 31 1669 [by] Ezekiel Hopkins.</title>
            <author>Hopkins, Ezekiel, 1634-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44441</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18202279</idno>
  <idno type="VID">107038</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240905245</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2738</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R235515</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">18202279</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44441)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107038)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1125:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Christs Church in Dublin, Jan. 31 1669 [by] Ezekiel Hopkins.</title>
                  <author>Hopkins, Ezekiel, 1634-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Benjamin Tooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by Order."</note>
                  <note>Includes marginal notes in Latin.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1].</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 1st, III, 13-14 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107038:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at Christs Church IN DUBLIN, <hi>Jan.</hi> 31 1669.</p>
            <p>EZEKIEL HOPKINS.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license" subtype="order_to_print">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Published by Order.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>DƲBLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty, And are to be sold by <hi>Mary Crooke</hi> in <hi>Castle-street.</hi> 1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:107038:2"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAg.</hi> 1 <hi>lin.</hi> 8 <hi>read</hi> Amercement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 20 <hi>lin.</hi> 13 <hi>read</hi> these.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 25 <hi>lin.</hi> 1 <hi>read</hi> thy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ib. lin.</hi> 2 <hi>for distinguish, read</hi> disintangle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 38 <hi>lin.</hi> 20 <hi>read</hi> spilt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:107038:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:107038:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107038:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 PET. II.xiii, xiv.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Submit your selves to every Ordinance of man, for the Lords sake. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be to the King as supream; or unto Governours, as unto them who are sent by him for the punishment of evil doers, and for the praise of those that do well.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere nothing else required to a day of Humiliation, but the Solemnity of publick <hi>sorrow,</hi> and a <hi>sad</hi> review of former miscarriages: if a Fast did onely lay a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute upon our eyes; and tears, were the whole amecement of our crimes; I my self should have judged the Text now read,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107038:4"/> much improper to the occasion; and should rather have chosen some of those passionate lamentations, that might have opened a fountain in every eye, to floud this place, and turn it into a <hi>Bochim.</hi> But because the best sorrow is amendment, and <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> the truest Repentance, I therefore thought our most unfeigned mourning for a <hi>slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred Monarch,</hi> would be to learn, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice our duty to the <hi>living.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I believe there are none of us here, but do from our very hearts detest, and execrate that horrid vilany, which we this day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile; and account those hands accursed that were so impiously imbrewed in the Royal, and Sacred bloud of <hi>their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign,</hi> and <hi>Gods Anointed.</hi> Let us therefore testifie our abhorrence of that bloudy crime by our present submission: and by our chearful obedience, if not <hi>expiate the sin,</hi> and guilt; yet in some measure <hi>redeem the credit, and glory</hi> of these Nations.</p>
            <p>I have therefore pitcht upon these words of the Apostle, <hi>Submit your selves to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ordinance of man, for the Lords sake,</hi> &amp;c. And they are one of those many rules, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed in this latter part of the Chapter for the right ordering of a Christian conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107038:4"/> that it might be blameless, and inof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensive.</p>
            <p>For though it were both the primitive Principle and Practice, in all <hi>lawfull things,</hi> to yield ready obedience to the will and command of their Magistrates; and in all <hi>unlawfull,</hi> chearfully to devote themselves to sufferings: yet (as appears by their Apologies) they were clamoured against by the heathens, as heady, and seditious, authors and leaders of factions, distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the publick peace, and pestilent ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the State. This accusation was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together undeserved, and indeed incongru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous both to their temper, and the rules of their Profession. It was a very unlikely thing, that <hi>they</hi> should aim at worldly greatness, whose first entrance into Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity was the renouncing of the world: that <hi>they</hi> should imbroil the State in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion against their Prince, who never lift up their hands, but in prayers to God for him; that <hi>they</hi> should intend to get the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty, and Dominion to themselves, who never thought of any other Crown, but of martyrdom, and that which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon it, of Glory. They were not such martial and fighting Christians, as the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107038:5"/> men of our times. And we may well won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if this Generation, who have been so hot, and fiery about little circumstances, and thought the debate of a Rite, or the mode of Discipline, cause enough, to warrant arms, and blood, and the ruins of Kingdoms; if they had lived in those primitive and Apostolical days, how they would have comported themselves under the Tyranny, and Cruelty of their heathen Emperours. Certainly, if onely a conceit and fancy of Superstition, could now leavy Armies, and draw out the sword against those, who were acknowledgedly of the same Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and Faith with themselves, who held the same <hi>Profession,</hi> the same <hi>Baptism,</hi> the same <hi>Head,</hi> the same <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Father of all,</hi> and agreed in all the substantials of one, and the <hi>same Religion;</hi> we may well think they would have flown out into all the extremities of blood and violence, when no other choice lay before them, but either <hi>Death,</hi> or <hi>Idolatry.</hi> Those who could now think it <hi>lawful</hi> to depose and murder a <hi>Christian King,</hi> would, no doubt, have thought it <hi>meritorious</hi> to assassinate a <hi>Pagan Persecutor.</hi> The Church had been then <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant</hi> in another sense, than it was: and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107038:5"/> Christ might have had <hi>many Hectors,</hi> but <hi>few Martyrs.</hi> No; the mild and calm Spirit of the Gospel taught them otherwise. Fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or dying were their onely refuges; and prayers, and tears their onely weapons. To read the histories of those first days of the Church, is but to wade so far in blood. Such multitudes perisht, of each sex, of all ages, by wild beasts, by fire, by the Cross, by the sword, by all the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Quid sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis de carne cum suppliciis erogatur, eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa reddere Christo vicem moriendi pro ipso, &amp; qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem per ean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem crucem saepe, nedum per atrociora quoque ingenia poenarum. <hi>Tertul de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrect.</hi>
               </note> witty cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties, that rage could invent, or power execute, that it is a wonder there were Persecutors enough to destroy them; and a farr greater wonder that there were any left to succeed in the profession of the same faith. But it was here true, which one of them said, <hi>Sanguis Martyrum est semen Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clefiae; The bloud of Martyrs is the seed of the Church:</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Ligaban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, iuclude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur, caede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebantur, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebantur, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niabantur, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidabantur, &amp; multiplicaban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, <hi>Aug. de Civit. Dei lib. 28 cap. 6.</hi>
               </note> whence sprung up such a numerous company of Confessors, as by their invincible patience, not by oppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and resistance, wearied out their Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menters, who had not strength enough to <hi>inflict,</hi> what the Christians had strength enough to <hi>suffer.</hi> Yea so <hi>thick</hi> was this <hi>seed</hi> sown, that<note n="(c)" place="margin">Hieron. Epistol. ad <hi>Chromatium</hi> &amp; <hi>Heliodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Jerome</hi> assignes no less than the bloud of <hi>five thousand</hi> Martyrs, to every day in the year; onely excepting
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107038:6"/> the first of <hi>January</hi> from so deep a <hi>Rubrick:</hi> And that which I cannot but account the hardest and sorest tryal of their patience, was, that whensoever it pleased Almighty God to send any notable plague upon the world, as sickness, or drowth, or famine; whensoever the Sea, or Rivers broke out, or a worse deluge of Barbarous, and Savage Nations broke in, upon the Roman Confines, streight the out-cry of the Rabble was, <hi>Christianos ad Leones, Away with the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians to the Lyons,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> witnesseth in his <hi>Apologetick:</hi> streight the anger of the Gods must be appeased with the bloud of Christians, who for refusing to <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> must themselves be made vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctimes.</p>
            <p>Now, though it be a great provocation to <hi>become</hi> turbulent and seditious, when men are <hi>causlesly</hi> suspected, and punisht as such already: yet, saith our Apostle, though you are so dealt with, spoken against and Persecuted as evil doers, herein shew your selves to be Christians, that aim at greater matters than what your Emperours are jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous you will attempt to take from them; and be not onely <hi>victorious in your Constancy</hi> under <hi>sufferings,</hi> but <hi>loyal</hi> also <hi>in your Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:107038:6"/> under <hi>suspicions,</hi> and <hi>false accusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Though they speak against you as evil doers, as it is</hi> vers. 12. <hi>Yet submit your selves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords sake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words contain in them.</p>
            <p>First, An <hi>Authoritative Command</hi> of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Submit your selves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>Object</hi> to which this Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> must be yeilded. <hi>Every Ordinance of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>division</hi> of this Ordinance <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of man into <hi>supreme, and subordinate. Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the King as supream, and to Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours sent by him, as subordinate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, We have the <hi>Duty</hi> of all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and the <hi>end</hi> of all Government ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest; and that is, <hi>The punishment of evil doers, and the praise of them that do well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, We have the <hi>Motive</hi> that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forceth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> this Exhortation and Command. <hi>Submit to them for the Lords sake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are but two Terms in the Text that require explication. The one is, what is meant by <hi>every Ordinance of man.</hi> The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, what force lyes in that adjuring ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, <hi>For the Lords sake.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:107038:7"/>
            <p>As to the former; <hi>Every Ordinance of man</hi> may be taken, either.</p>
            <p>First, For every <hi>Edict and Constitution, every Law and Command</hi> that issues forth from those that are in Authority over us. Called therefore an <hi>Ordinance of man,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause invigorated by humane Authority. Or</p>
            <p>Secondly, It may be taken for <hi>Magistrates</hi> themselves. And indeed thus it ought to be understood in this place. And so the sense is this: Whatsoever lawful form of Magistracy or Government you live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>Submit</hi> your selves unto it. And it is here called <hi>an Ordinance of man,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>an humane creature,</hi> not as though Magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy were onely an humane Invention, or a creature of mans making. For so St. <hi>Peter</hi> should contradict St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who tells us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>There are no powers but of God, the powers that be are ordained of God; and he that resisteth the power, resisteth the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God.</hi> But yet this <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> is here called <hi>an Ordinance of man;</hi> both because it is appointed among men, and for the good of men: and because like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the several forms of Government were at first modell'd according as humane pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107038:7"/> and convenience dictated. <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracy</hi> is an <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> in respect of its <hi>original Institution:</hi> but it is an <hi>Ordinance of man,</hi> in respect of its <hi>particular Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and Modification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then as for the <hi>Motive, Submit your selves for the Lords sake;</hi> This can bear no other sense, than upon the account of Gods Command, as you would do an acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable service to him. And it is tantamount to that other place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5. <hi>You must needs be subject, not onely for wrath,</hi> i. e. for fear of the Princes wrath, and the direful ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects that may follow upon it in case of diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; <hi>but also for Conscience sake:</hi> i. e. because of those obligations which lie upon Conscience from Gods commands. For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be done for Conscience sake, which is not done out of respect to Gods Authority, who is the onely supream Lord of Conscience, and hath strictly bound it to all duties of submission to his under Officers, and Vicegerents upon earth. So that diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the <hi>Ordinance of man,</hi> rests not there, but becomes Rebellion against God himself. Princes rule by vertue of Gods Commission and Authority; they are his Lieutenants in the world, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107038:8"/> therefore to disobey them, is to rebel against that Sovereign and Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority by which they reign.</p>
            <p>Hence therefore let us observe; <hi>That Obedience to earthly Kings and Governours is a duty we owe to them, and not to them onely, but to the great King, and Governor of Heaven and Earth. Submit your selves for the Lords sake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man was at first created after the image and similitude of God; and one great part of that Image consisted in his <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> over the Creatures. But Kings in this particular approach much nearer unto the Divine resemblance, and have <hi>fairer strokes</hi> of this Image drawn upon them than other men. They are raised in power and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, not onely over the <hi>brute</hi> and <hi>irrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Creatures,</hi> as others are; but over <hi>men</hi> themselves, and are <hi>Lords of those,</hi> who are <hi>Lords of the world.</hi> As <hi>Adam</hi> was therefore like unto God, because inferiour to none, but him: so are they. The Image of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity is so conspicuous in their Dominion and Soveraignty, that upon this very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count alone, God takes them into co-part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nership of that glorious name, whereby himself is known, <hi>Psal.</hi> 82.6. <hi>I have said
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107038:8"/> ye are Gods.</hi> Whatsoever they be for other indowments; whether vertuous, or vicious, Persecuters, or Favourers of Religion; yet in respect of Soveraignty, and Dominion, they are the visible Images and lively pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traicts of God upon Earth.</p>
            <p>Now as a contumely, or dishonour done to the Image or statue of a man; redounds onely to the dishonour of the Person, whom it represents (and therefore States, to punish those who are either dead, or fled out of their reach, have been oftentimes known publickly to execute their Pictures) so it is here: Disobedience to the lawfull Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate reflects contempt upon God himself, whose Image the Magistrate is: and by <hi>des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pising Government, and speaking evil of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities,</hi> they onely invent a way how they may rebell against, and depose God <hi>in Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is not my design to make a <hi>Panegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> in magnifying Kingly power; but rather to give some Instructions, concerning that <hi>submission</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> which we owe unto it upon the command of God. Never cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly was it more needful than now, rightly to state how farr, and upon what grounds we are obliged to obey the <hi>Powers</hi> that God
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107038:9"/> hath set over us. Which possibly we may gain some light to discern by a thorough sifting of these following distinctions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> First we must distinguish of <hi>Rulers:</hi> For they are either <hi>lawful Magistrates,</hi> or <hi>Ʋsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</hi> And blessed be God, that we may now without danger, make such a distincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as this is.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, As <hi>they,</hi> so their <hi>Commands</hi> may be either <hi>lawfull, or unlawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Obedience to their lawful commands may be considered as due, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in point of <hi>Prudence;</hi> or else in point of <hi>Conscience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Obedience in point of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, is either <hi>Active,</hi> in performing what is required; or <hi>Passive</hi> in suffering what is threatned.</p>
            <p>Out of these <hi>Distinctions,</hi> I shall form several <hi>Propositions,</hi> resolutory (as I hope) to my subject in hand.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> First, Therefore, No subjection is due to an <hi>unlawful and Ʋsurping Power,</hi> upon <hi>Gods Command,</hi> and <hi>for Conscience sake.</hi> Some of late years who have been mighty loth <hi>to dispute Titles</hi> against their present Interest and advantage, have earnestly opposed this Assertion: affirming that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107038:9"/>
               <hi>Ʋsurped Power</hi> though it be <hi>unlawful</hi> in the <hi>Acquisition;</hi> yet becomes so farr <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> when <hi>acquired,</hi> as to oblige Conscience it self to submission. A strange and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surd opinion this; as if that became law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful by being <hi>accomplisht,</hi> which was wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and sinful in being but <hi>attempted.</hi> Then must <hi>prosperous</hi> wickedness, hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be taken for vertue: and the onely way to <hi>justifie</hi> a bad undertaking must be to go <hi>thorough with it.</hi> No, It is not a <hi>rude, boistrous Power,</hi> that may perhaps be like an irresistible Torrent, and bear down all before it; it is not this, but <hi>Right,</hi> and <hi>Title</hi> that invests a <hi>Magistrate.</hi> Magistra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Authority, is too <hi>Sacred a thing</hi> to be intaild upon the <hi>longest sword,</hi> and the <hi>strongest arm.</hi> And certainly if actual possession of Sovereignty can make good any <hi>Ʋsurpers</hi> Title unto it, and make him <hi>the power ordained of God,</hi> by the same reason may any plead Title to your houses and estates, who can either by force, or fraud make entry upon them.</p>
            <p>But yet as absurd as this Doctrine is, <hi>Scripture</hi> is alledged for it: and of all, that place is especially insisted on, <hi>Rom.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:107038:10"/> 13.1. <hi>There is no power but of God, the powers that be, are ordained of God</hi> Hence they collect, that the <hi>very Being or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>istence of a Power,</hi> makes it the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> and obligeth even <hi>Conscience</hi> it self to Obedience. But here, it is not the Apostles intent to assert, that the <hi>Being</hi> of a Power makes it lawful; but that those <hi>lawful Powers that are,</hi> are Gods Ordinance and appointment. And this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> First, Because the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; which is here translated Power, is not any where used in the New Testament; but onely to signifie <hi>Authority and a lawful Power.</hi> Yea, when the <hi>Devil</hi> himself used it; <hi>Luke</hi> 4.6. He would willingly have had our Saviour understood him in this sence. And not to insist on this, the very nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it from the verb <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Licet,</hi> proves the onely proper use of it to be for <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, This <hi>Power</hi> which the Text speaks of, is such as may <hi>not be resisted. Whosoever resisteth the Power, resisteth the Ordinance of God: and they that resist, shall receive unto themselves damnation, verse</hi> 2. But now that Power which hath
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107038:10"/> no Title to Sovereignty, besides present Possession, may be <hi>lawfully resisted,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the sad doom of incurring damnation for so doing. What frequent instances have we in the Book of <hi>Judges,</hi> of the revolutions of the Israelites affairs. Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Possession, and under the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression of their neighbouring Kings, till God raised them up deliverers to rescue them from that bondage, and slavery. They did not think they were for <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi> or for <hi>Gods sake,</hi> bound to obey the usurping Powers they were at times under. No, though their Usurpers might plead, sometimes Twenty, sometimes Forty years prescription to strengthen their Title. Not to instance in all the particulars I might, (for that would be too tedious) what shall we think of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoiada</hi>'s proceedings, not onely in <hi>resist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> but in <hi>deposing, and putting Athaliah to death.</hi> Clear it is, that she had the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty in Possession, and stood seiz'd of it above six years. Yet none (I hope) will affirm, that <hi>Jehoiada resisted Gods Ordinance,</hi> or incurred <hi>damnation,</hi> by depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing her, and restoring his rightful Prince. Again</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:107038:11"/>
            <p>Thirdly, Since the onely Title that an <hi>Ʋsurper</hi> hath to Soveraignty, is his <hi>resisting,</hi> and destroying the lawful power, it will follow, that a damnable act, as this is, may of it self conferr a <hi>lawful power,</hi> if invasion, or possession alone can make it such, which is an opinion so wild, that sobriety, and reason abhorr it. 'Tis true indeed, many have been rightful Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns, who ascended the Throne by fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitious Crimes, and the murder of their Predecessors: but yet the Title could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be devolved upon them by their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness, but either by Elective, or Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary succession. They have resisted, and destroyed the lawful Powers, onely to make way for their own Title to take place; but never can it be conceived, that Rebellion should give a Title; or that God should give a man such a form of Deputation, as doth at once <hi>confirm</hi> his <hi>Authority,</hi> and <hi>Seal</hi> his <hi>damnation.</hi> It is evident therefore that lawful Soveraignty is not founded upon actual possession, but a fixt and setled right; and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly where ever an Usurping Power is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc't, neither God, nor Conscience require submission to it.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:107038:11"/>
            <p>And yet to give the contrary opinion some plausible colour, it is here objected, that <hi>those very persons</hi> which the Apostle speaks of, and which the believing Romans ought not to resist upon pain of Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, were but <hi>Ʋsurpers:</hi> the <hi>Caesars</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truding by force and violence, and the ruine of the Commonwealth, into the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Authority.</p>
            <p>To this may be answered, That not to dispute their right in first <hi>seising</hi> of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> which possibly (as I think in most, if not all other Governments) might be unjust enough, yet it is certain, and as clear as History can make any thing, that they were by the free votes both of <hi>Senate</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> and all the Authority of that <hi>State</hi> setled and acknowledged for their rightful Magistrates, and injoyed the Title and Power for some succession of Emperours, before the Apostle wrote this Epistle. And therefore Obedience was due to them, upon the account of <hi>Conscience,</hi> and <hi>for Gods sake.</hi> But it no way follows, that because the <hi>Powers</hi> that <hi>then were,</hi> were Gods Ordinance, that therefore <hi>every Power</hi> that is at any
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107038:12"/> time <hi>existent,</hi> must needs be so too. That's the first Position.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Upon <hi>prudential</hi> and self-preserving Principles, Submission may sometimes be yielded to the <hi>lawful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> of an unlawful and usurping Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <hi>Lawful commands</hi> I call them, not as though such had any right to command, but because they may command that which is right, and lawful to be done. Now though it be every mans duty, by all likely and probable means, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the suppression of an usurping Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; yet <hi>Prudence,</hi> and that Soveraign Law of <hi>self preservation</hi> must dictate to him the way and manner how it may be accomplisht, which till it be found <hi>feasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> it is but precipitateness for any man to oppose himself <hi>naked</hi> and <hi>defenceless</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>armed</hi> violence. This rashness doth but <hi>throw away</hi> a life, which if preserved till fairer opportunity presents it self, might become greatly serviceable to the rightful Prince, and instead of deposing, doth but <hi>secure</hi> the Usurper, alarming him against the future attempts of others, to which <hi>Confidence, and security</hi> might else expose him. And therefore <hi>Jehojada</hi> did not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107038:12"/> declare against <hi>Athaliah</hi> till he had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged the Officers of the Army, and layd his combination so, as reason might vote it would prove successful. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and too much already of <hi>Ʋsurped Powers,</hi> Therefore</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We ought to obey the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of the lawful Magistrate in those things which are in themselves <hi>necessary</hi> to be done, and our <hi>indispensable duty;</hi> and that not only out of <hi>Conscience to God,</hi> but also out of <hi>Conscience to him.</hi> Such are all the duties of the law, of nature, and of the written law of God, which the Magistrate ought to inforce upon us by his Authority: for he is <hi>Custos utrius{que} tabulae, the Guardian of both Tables of the Law.</hi> And though the duties therein prescribed, do before hand bind the Conscience to the practice of them; yet also is the guilt of trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressing them, aggravated by the additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Magistrates commands: and it is no contemptible security added to the Laws of God, when they have a <hi>Guard</hi> of humane Laws set about them; and none can violate the Laws of God, but he he must also wrong and violate the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107038:13"/> Authority of his Prince. As for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, we ought to <hi>worship God</hi> after a right and due manner; we ought to <hi>honour our Parents, to abstain from theft, murder, and adultery,</hi> though there were no humane Laws to require it from us. But yet when the Magistrate shall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose <hi>his Authority,</hi> and injoyn the very same; these duties lye then more <hi>pressing</hi> and <hi>binding</hi> upon our Consciences. For then the strength of divers Commands is put together <hi>into one;</hi> and we are <hi>doubly</hi> obliged to their duties, both by <hi>these Laws</hi> of God which expresly require them; and also by <hi>another Law</hi> of God, which requires <hi>Obedience</hi> to our <hi>Magistrates.</hi> Of this I think, there is no doubt at all made, and therefore.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If the thing commanded be <hi>indifferently lawful,</hi> and <hi>appear so to us;</hi> that is, if it be in its own nature such as we may either do it, or not do it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out sin; then are we to be determined by the Magistrates Commands to do what he requires, and to abstain from what he forbids. For though after the Magistrate hath interposed his Authority, the thing remains in it self still <hi>indifferent,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:107038:13"/> yet it no longer remains <hi>so,</hi> as to our practice; but it is a sin in us, not to do what lawfully we may when he requires it. For I suppose a Magistrate hath a greater Command over his Subjects, than any Father hath over his children; since the Magistrate is the <hi>Common Father, Pater Patriae,</hi> and Children are bound to obey him, rather than their Parents, when their Commands contradict one the other. Now which of you doth not assume to himself such an authority over his Child, as to think him bound in duty, to do that upon your Command, which before you commanded him, was meerly indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and might either be done by him, or not done. The same obedience there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which you expect from your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in things indifferent, the same you owe to your Prince, and the Authority that is over you.</p>
            <p>And therefore it is a most <hi>absurd</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which some have taken up, that things in themselves <hi>indifferent,</hi> become <hi>unlawful</hi> when <hi>imposed.</hi> As if that were <hi>unlawful</hi> to be done when <hi>commanded,</hi> which was <hi>lawful</hi> to be done, even <hi>without a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand:</hi> or any thing could be lawful,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107038:14"/> when onely <hi>permitted;</hi> but sinful, when <hi>injoyned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as it is hugely <hi>absurd</hi> and <hi>irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> so it is very <hi>dangerous</hi> and <hi>pernicious:</hi> For it cuts the very finews, and plucks up the very roots of Government. It cashiers and abrogates the farr greater part of all humane <hi>Laws;</hi> and abridgeth the Magistrates Authority, in injoyning any thing, but express duties, commanded before of God in Scripture.</p>
            <p>And see what a <hi>wild consequence</hi> will follow upon this <hi>Tenent:</hi> For if things <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently lawful,</hi> become <hi>sinful</hi> when <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed,</hi> then by the same reason they must needs become <hi>necessary,</hi> when they are <hi>forbidden.</hi> And so consequently, whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever of this nature the Magistrate shall forbid, men must look upon themselves as bound in Conscience to practice: and what <hi>Monsters</hi> lye in the womb of this consequence, any understanding man may at first glance perceive. What is this, but to spell the Magistrates Authority <hi>back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards;</hi> and to give him that power over your Consciences by his <hi>Prohibitions,</hi> which you deny to his <hi>Commands</hi> and <hi>Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</hi> This <hi>Tenent</hi> therefore is most <hi>ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous;</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:107038:14"/> most <hi>foolish,</hi> and most <hi>pernicious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ought then in all things, which are in themselves <hi>indifferent,</hi> and <hi>appear so to us,</hi> to give ready and chearful obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Commands of our lawful Magistrates; and that <hi>for the Lords sake.</hi> And here they are not little <hi>prejudices,</hi> nor little <hi>inconveniencies;</hi> because such a Command crosseth my <hi>former custome,</hi> or my <hi>present humour,</hi> that can supersede my obligation. No, nor is it lawful, without very great and pressing reasons, and almost a necessity, to chuse the <hi>pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive part</hi> of the Command, to undergo the <hi>Penalty,</hi> rather than fulfill the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept.</hi> And that because the Penalty is onely annexed, as the <hi>secondary will</hi> of the Magistrates, to inforce the Precept; nor doth the Law primarily aim at <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment,</hi> but at <hi>conformity</hi> to it. This is to be accounted the <hi>will</hi> of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, whose <hi>will</hi> is our <hi>Obligation</hi> in all things that are lawful and indifferent. And therefore to chuse the <hi>Penal,</hi> before the <hi>Preceptive</hi> part of Obedience, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out very weighty, and necessitating rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons urging us thereunto, cannot altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be excused from <hi>Disobedience;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:107038:15"/> it comes not up to that Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which the Magistrate principally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends. That's the fourth Position.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, If the thing be indifferently lawful in it self; but appears <hi>doubtful</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, and we cannot resolve our selves whether it be lawful, or evil; I think we are obliged (till we receive clearer light, and information) to take <hi>that part</hi> of the doubt, which the Magistrate commands us, as being the safest, and most satisfactory to Conscience. And my reason is this; Because the Obligation that lies upon us to <hi>obey</hi> the Magistrates Commands, is <hi>certain;</hi> but the <hi>unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> of what thou <hi>doubtest</hi> is <hi>not so:</hi> and therefore his Authority ought to prepon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate with us, and make that our <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted duty,</hi> which was before, but a <hi>doubted and suspected sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed the <hi>Apostle</hi> tells us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. <hi>That whatsoever is not of Faith, i. e.</hi> whatsoever is not done, or forborn with a rational perswasion of the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of doing or forbearing it, <hi>is sin:</hi> and that <hi>whosoever doubteth is damned if he eat.</hi> But in this case, the Magistrates Commands do not ingage thee to do any
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107038:15"/> thing <hi>doubting,</hi> but rather will solve thy <hi>doubts,</hi> and distinguish thee from the snare in which thy Conscience was held. For though the nature of the thing be not at all <hi>changed</hi> by his Commands, yet thy doubtful mind may be well <hi>setled:</hi> for <hi>upon his Command,</hi> thou hast reason to think that thy <hi>duty,</hi> which <hi>before his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> thou couldst not absolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude to be a <hi>sin.</hi> That's a fifth Position.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, If the thing injoyned, be in it self <hi>sinful, and unlawful,</hi> or at least <hi>appear <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> so</hi> unto us, then take these two following Rules.</p>
            <p>First we ought not upon any preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> or inducements whatsoever, to yield <hi>Active obedience</hi> to such a Command. In this case, that plea of the Apostle holds good, and will do so ever, <hi>Acts,</hi> 5.29. <hi>We ought to obey God rather then men.</hi> And <hi>Acts,</hi> 4.19. <hi>Wether it be right in the sight of God to hearken unto you, more than unto God, judge ye.</hi> And in this case, it was no <hi>rude,</hi> nor <hi>uncivil,</hi> but a <hi>noble</hi> and truly <hi>Heroick</hi> answer which the <hi>three Worthies</hi> gave unto <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, Dan.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Be it known unto thee O King, that we will not serve thy Gods, nor worship thy golden
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:107038:16"/> Image, which thou hast set up.</hi> For when Princes commands contradict the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God, they carry no Authority in them to inforce our <hi>Active obedience;</hi> no more than the Commands of an <hi>infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Magistrate</hi> do, when they contradict the Laws of the <hi>supream.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea we are not to yield <hi>Active obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> not onely when their commands <hi>are</hi> expresly against the commands of God; but when we are verily in our own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences <hi>so perswaded.</hi> For Conscience rules us in Gods name; and whatsoever it <hi>Dictates,</hi> it believes to be the very will and mind of God. And therefore to slight the voice of Conscience, is interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatively to slight the voice of God. And those who will not follow the voice of Conscience, when <hi>they believe</hi> its dictates to be the will of God, would not follow them, though indeed <hi>they were so.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then we must be sure that we have express word and warrant from God; and not take up with doubtful and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure Texts, and more doubtful and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote consequences to dispense with us from that obedience, which is evidently and frequently required. But</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:107038:16"/>
            <p>Secondly, Though we may not yield <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>Active obedience</hi> to the unlawful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of our Superiours, yet we are bound to yield <hi>Passive obedience</hi> to them. For all humane Laws consist of a <hi>Precept,</hi> and a <hi>penalty;</hi> where the <hi>Precept</hi> may not be <hi>obeyed,</hi> yet the <hi>Penalty</hi> must be <hi>submitted to,</hi> with all patience and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, though it reach to the loss of our Estates, or of our liberty, yea the dearest of all our possessions, life it self; unless we can prudently with-draw our selves, and avoid their rage by flight. That's the <hi>sixth Position.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, and lastly, we ought in no case whatsoever to <hi>resist,</hi> and <hi>rebell against</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> the lawful Powers that God hath set o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us; yea though they should use their power <hi>unlawfully. For whosoever resist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Power, resisteth the Ordinance of God. And they that resist, shall receive to themselves damnation.</hi> As it is in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of a State or Nation, if any <hi>infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Magistrate</hi> abuse his power over thee, thou art not presently to oppose him by any violent or illegal proceedings, nor to make any insurrection against him, and pull him off his Tribunal, or divest him of his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; but appeal to the <hi>Prince and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107038:17"/> Magistrate,</hi> for redress of those wrongs: so likewise here, if the <hi>supream Magistrate</hi> should abuse his Soveraign Power, and command thee to do what God, his superiour, hath commanded thee not to do, and shall punish thee for not obeying him, and offending God; thou art not to <hi>resist,</hi> nor make conspiracies against him, nor to raise tumults and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions to depose him from his Authority; but onely quietly and meekly to <hi>appeal</hi> unto God, who alone is his <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Ruler,</hi> and to beg him to take thy cause into his cognizance, and redress thy wrongs and injuries.</p>
            <p>Yea put the case as high as we can; suppose that Christian Subjects should live under the Dominion of a Prince, who, as he is a <hi>God</hi> in respect of <hi>Power,</hi> so he is a <hi>Devil</hi> in respect of <hi>Cruelty,</hi> and <hi>mischief.</hi> Suppose the two worst cases that can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> First, That he should injoyn them <hi>su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition and Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, That he should oppress them by <hi>Persecution and Tyranny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ever there were a specious pretence for Subjects to say, <hi>shall I smite him, shall
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:107038:17"/> I smite him,</hi> it is in this supposition. Here seems the best cause and the highest equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the world, to deliver the <hi>world</hi> from a <hi>Monster,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> from a <hi>Devil,</hi> Yet I say, neither of these can justifie <hi>Rebellion</hi> against him, or <hi>Revenge</hi> upon him. Was there ever a more accomplisht and consummate wretch than <hi>Nero?</hi> A man that made the <hi>Martyrdom</hi> of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans his <hi>pastime;</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Pereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus (Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anis) ludibria addita, ut fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum tergis contecti, lani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atu canum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terirent, aut crucibus affixi aut flamman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di; at{que} ubi defecisset dies, in usumnoctur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni luminis urerentur. Tacit. Annal. lib. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> and burnt them in the streets of <hi>Rome</hi> to light him from the stewes. And yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> commands the Roman Christians to submit <hi>to him for Conscience sake,</hi> and threatens them with <hi>Damnation</hi> if they <hi>resist.</hi> No, we ought in this case (though it be farr from the fiery spirit of our times) to <hi>receive blows,</hi> but not to <hi>strike again,</hi> and rather to indure the greatest of Cruelties, then lift up our hands to revenge them.</p>
            <p>And indeed there is a great deal of Reason for it. For</p>
            <p>First, <hi>Punishment</hi> is an Act of <hi>venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</hi> Now Revenge is such a wild un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamed thing, that God hath not trusted it in any private hands, but reserved it to himself, who can best dispense and govern it. <hi>Vengeance is mine, saith the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:107038:18"/> Lord, and I will repay it. Rom.</hi> 12.19. So that none ought to intermeddle with this part of Justice, but those whom God hath impower'd thereunto, and made his Substitute officers, and Ministers to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pense it, and that is onely the Magistrate. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. <hi>He is the Minister of God, a Revenger to execute wrath upon him that doth evil.</hi> None are to be <hi>Revengers,</hi> but <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Magistrates.</hi> Magistrates up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>evil men:</hi> and God upon <hi>evil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates.</hi> Private Christians have nothing to do with <hi>Revenge,</hi> or punishment; no, not to inflict it one upon another; much less upon their <hi>Rulers:</hi> and if they do; as they <hi>Rebel</hi> against <hi>men,</hi> so they <hi>usurp</hi> upon God, and put themselves in his stead.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Princes are <hi>supream</hi> to all, but God; and therefore <hi>accountable</hi> to none besides him. All humane power is <hi>subordinate</hi> to theirs, and <hi>derived</hi> from it: for from the <hi>chief,</hi> do <hi>other</hi> Magistrates re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Authority, and Commission; and therefore cannot any humane Power punish those, on whose Authority they depend.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, What a wide gap for all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107038:18"/> of <hi>confusion,</hi> and <hi>disorder,</hi> would this open to the world! who, that fancies himself aggrieved and wrong'd, would not presently make a party, and sound the Trumpet, and proclaim that he had equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and justice on his side, and so hurl all into <hi>Tumults</hi> and wild <hi>confusion?</hi> But though thou maist have suffered real in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice; yet thou oughtest not to rebel. The wiseman hath long since condemned the <hi>striking of Princes for equity,</hi> Prov. 17.26. Whether for <hi>their equities</hi> sake, or <hi>thine.</hi> And the Apostle reckons it the <hi>glory</hi> of a Christian, and an acceptable <hi>service</hi> to God patiently to indure when we <hi>suffer evil</hi> for <hi>doing well.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19, 20, 21. <hi>What glory is it if when ye be buffeted for your faults, ye shall take it pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently? but if when ye do well, and suffer for it, ye take it patiently; this is accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with God. For even hereunto were ye called: because also Christ suffered for us, leaving us an example, that ye should fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his steps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea even <hi>Religion,</hi> the best and most precious of all our enjoyments, is too weak a cause to justifie Rebellion, and insurrections. To think that upon the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:107038:19"/> account of <hi>Religion,</hi> or any form, or mode either of worship, or Discipline, that men are zealous for, they may lawfuly oppose, yea and depose the Authority that God hath set over them, is a Tenent utterly <hi>irreligious.</hi> And truly Religion can never so much suffer by the fiercest <hi>Persecution,</hi> as by such wild and rebellious <hi>Principles.</hi> It is a Doctrine quite contrary to the true <hi>Genius</hi> and <hi>Constitution</hi> of Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. In the primitive times, for the long space of three <hi>hundred years,</hi> till at length the <hi>Roman Emperours</hi> gave up their names to <hi>Christ,</hi> those who commanded the whole world, set all their wit and force to <hi>crush</hi> this <hi>growing Doctrine;</hi> but were still dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed in this attempt, whence this defeat? was it because they were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born by the too powerful <hi>resistance</hi> that the Christians made against them? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing less<note n="(a)" place="margin">Si enim hostes apertos, non tantum vindicesoce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos agere vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemus, deesset nobis vis nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merorum &amp; copiarum? Plures nimirum Mauri &amp; Marcomanni, ipsi{que} Parthi, vel quantaecun{que} unius tamen loci, &amp; suorum finium gentes, quam totius orbis? Externi sumus &amp; vestra omnia im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plevimus, urbes, insulas, castella, municipia, conciliabula, castra ipsa, tribus, decurias, palatium, senatum, sorum; sola vobis reliquimus Templa. Cui bello non idonei, non prompti fuissemus, etiam copiis impares, qui tam li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enter trucidamur, si non apud islam disciplinam, magis occidi liceret quam occidere? Tertul. Apol.</note> For though almost every City, every Village, every Family; yea their Camps, and Armies abounded with Christians, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> witnesseth in his <hi>Apologetick;</hi> yet under all those savage
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:107038:19"/> and barbarous presecutions, that butcher'd them up <hi>like sheep appointed to the slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> we never read of any <hi>insur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> against the lawful Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Circa Majestatem Imperatoris infamamur; tamen unúquam Albiniani, vel Nigriani, vel Cassiani, in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e runt Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. Tertul ad scapulam, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ij, &amp; Nigri, &amp; Albini? unde qui inter duas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obsident Caesarem? Ʋnde qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aucibus ejus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primendis palaestricam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rcent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> De Romanis, ni fallor, id est, de non Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. Tert. Apol. vid. Aug. de civ. Dei. l. <hi>22.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Nay the <hi>Fathers</hi> boast and glory of this <hi>conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring patience</hi> of the Christians, and <hi>challenge</hi> the Heathen to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any one instance of a <hi>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny</hi> or <hi>sedition,</hi> wherein a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian was ingaged.<note n="(c)" place="margin">No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nos adversum te Imperator, armavit ipsa, quae fortissima est in periculis desperatio. Tenemus ecce arma, &amp; non resistimus, quia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>i m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, quam vincere volumus, &amp; innocentes inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m noxij vivere prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptamus. Exuperius le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis Thebaea signifer, ad Maximinian.</note> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing their vast <hi>numbers,</hi> that might make them <hi>potent;</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding they were all <hi>devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ruine and destruction,</hi> which might make them <hi>desperate,</hi> and <hi>despair</hi> added to <hi>power</hi> makes it <hi>invincible;</hi> yet we read of no tumults, no uproars, no warrs raised by them in the State; for the Peace and Prosperity of which they prayed <hi>dying,</hi> and took the sword, rather into their <hi>throats,</hi> than into their <hi>hands:</hi> nor was it their method to propagate Christianity, and true Religion, by any other <hi>bloud,</hi> but their <hi>own.</hi> This was the way, by which the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, which <hi>sent</hi> more Christians to <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:107038:20"/> and <hi>gained</hi> more to be Christians on <hi>Earth,</hi> than ever the <hi>pomp,</hi> and <hi>splendour</hi> of it hath done since.</p>
            <p>This was the true Evangelical Spirit, which taught them to <hi>obey</hi> their Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates Commands, in what was <hi>lawful,</hi> and in what was <hi>otherwise,</hi> either <hi>prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> to <hi>avoid</hi> their rage by <hi>flight,</hi> or <hi>patiently</hi> to <hi>indure</hi> it by <hi>dying.</hi> They had not learn't that lirry, that the Saints are the onely Lords of the world; that all the <hi>ungodly</hi> (and all <hi>must</hi> be <hi>such,</hi> whom they pleased) were but <hi>Ʋsurpers</hi> and <hi>Intruders</hi> upon <hi>their Rights:</hi> That they must <hi>Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, Overturn, Overturn,</hi> to make way for the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Christ;</hi> intending, no doubt, to set themselves, one at <hi>his right hand,</hi> and another at <hi>his left,</hi> in that <hi>his Kingdom.</hi> The Doctrine of the Gospel taught them not these violent and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Principles; but it is as full of <hi>Peace</hi> as it is of <hi>Purity;</hi> and instructed them to <hi>acknowledg</hi> their Magistrates <hi>Authority,</hi> to <hi>pray</hi> for their <hi>Prosperity,</hi> to <hi>obey</hi> their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands <hi>chearfully,</hi> or <hi>quietly</hi> to <hi>suffer</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment: and this though they had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant <hi>Provocation to resist,</hi> and <hi>Probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of being <hi>successful.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:107038:20"/>
            <p>Much more <hi>damnable,</hi> therefore is it, when there is no such <hi>provocation</hi> given; when <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> and <hi>justice,</hi> are onely <hi>pretended;</hi> when <hi>Godly Princes</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their Conscience, and their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian duty in the Government committed unto them; much more <hi>damnable</hi> is it; I say, yea <hi>damnable</hi> to the utmost degree of <hi>damnation,</hi> for Subjects upon every whimsical discontent, to resist, imprison, depose, and murder them; while they cheat and cosen the world with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of <hi>Saints,</hi> but do the works of Devils.</p>
            <p>And now had this Doctrine been more prest, and more ponder'd of late years, we had not <hi>this day</hi> had this sad occasion to be humbled for the unparallel'd wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness of <hi>Yesterday.</hi> A day it was, that were it not it afforded us an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to testifie our abhorrency and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station of that bloudy vilany it once saw, we might well wish that the year would <hi>skip</hi> it over; and imprecate it as <hi>Job</hi> doth the day of his birth, Job. 3.3.4. <hi>Let that day perish, let it be darkness, let not God regard it, neither let the light shine upon it; let darkness, and the shadow of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:107038:21"/> death stain it, and a perpetual cloud dwell upon it.</hi> A day that hath brought an <hi>indelible blot and infamy</hi> upon these <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and made us a <hi>reproach and scorn</hi> to the whole world. And what is worse, it hath exposed <hi>Religion</hi> it self to <hi>contempt and hatred,</hi> and made it <hi>a reproach to scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> who whilest they saw those very men that so highly pretended <hi>Reformation, and the Power of Godliness,</hi> imbrew their hands in <hi>Royal and Sacred bloud,</hi> have been ready to conclude, that to profess <hi>Religion,</hi> is nothing else but to seek a <hi>varnish and colour</hi> for some black and horrid wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. This hath rendered the <hi>Reverend</hi> name of <hi>Godliness,</hi> despicable and odious to <hi>profane</hi> Spirits; who whilest they saw none <hi>priviledged</hi> to act their <hi>rapines, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, injustice, and most wrongful Ʋsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation and Tyranny,</hi> but those whose <hi>mouths</hi> were as full of a <hi>glorious Profession,</hi> as their <hi>hands:</hi> were of <hi>wicked deeds,</hi> have charged all those impieties upon the score of <hi>Religion,</hi> and made it bear the burthen of those <hi>Crimes</hi> with which it is not <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was once the glory of the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Religion,</hi> that it taught <hi>Subjects</hi> to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:107038:21"/> account the <hi>persons</hi> of their Princes <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred</hi> and <hi>Inviolable; supream</hi> to all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, and accountable to none but Him: and possibly this one <hi>Doctrine</hi> hath been no small advantage, to make it gain <hi>so much</hi> ground, in <hi>so short</hi> a space. But now our Adversaries triumph in the shame of our Profession, when the most <hi>notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Regicides,</hi> who not not onely <hi>avow the Doctrine</hi> but <hi>publickly perpetrate the fact</hi> of deposing and killing <hi>a King,</hi> are found among those who pretended to be at the greatest distance from <hi>Romish Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and practices.</hi> There is indeed a great difference between the Doctrine of a <hi>schism;</hi> and the Doctrine of a <hi>Church:</hi> between the practice of a <hi>Nation,</hi> and the practice of a prevalent <hi>Faction</hi> in the Nation. And blessed be God, we have this still left to silence the recriminations of all Antichristian Adversaries, that to <hi>depose</hi> and <hi>assassinate Kings,</hi> is not the Doctrine of the <hi>Protestant Church,</hi> but of the <hi>Romish Synagogue.</hi> And as it was not the Doctrine of the <hi>Church,</hi> but of a <hi>schism;</hi> so neither was it the <hi>Fact</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> but of a Rebellious and prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Faction</hi> in it; nor could their armed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:107038:22"/> violence reach the <hi>Head,</hi> till they had first destroyed the <hi>body</hi> both of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is not the work of this day to <hi>excuse any,</hi> but to <hi>stirr up all</hi> to bemoan this bloudy, and horrid Crime. A Crime the most horrid and accursed, that ever was acted under the <hi>Sun,</hi> but onely when a <hi>Miracle</hi> eclipst it from looking on. Though the Histories of all Nations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with the sad <hi>Tragedies</hi> of their lawful Princes assassinated by their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, yet we may still remarke that their wickedness was either so <hi>Timorous,</hi> or so <hi>Modest,</hi> as to indeavour to <hi>hide</hi> the bloud they <hi>shed,</hi> and durst not be otherwise <hi>guilty,</hi> but with those advantages of night and secrecy, that might make them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear <hi>Innocent.</hi> But here Royal and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred bloud is <hi>Theatrically</hi> split, and the <hi>Fact avowed</hi> by the impudent <hi>Pomp</hi> and <hi>Solemnity</hi> of vilany. Vilany so profligate that it scorn'd to proceed in <hi>a clandestine</hi> manner, but as it was resolved to <hi>out-do</hi> all the examples of former Regicides, so to <hi>out-face</hi> all that should dare to oppose or condemn it. And therefore to add <hi>Ceremony,</hi> and <hi>scorn</hi> to <hi>Murder,</hi> they erect
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:107038:22"/> a <hi>Pageantry</hi> of Justice; summon the <hi>Throne</hi> to appear before the <hi>Bar;</hi> arraign <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty,</hi> before which awe and reverence should have made them tremble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn <hi>him</hi> for their <hi>own Crimes;</hi> and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute that wicked Sentence with all the <hi>Ostentation</hi> that <hi>triumphant</hi> spight and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice could invent.</p>
            <p>And that which makes all this the more odious, and execrable, all this was transacted under <hi>forms of Justice,</hi> and <hi>specious pretexts of the Glory of God,</hi> and the Interests of Religion. Here the <hi>Faith</hi> bleeds bleeds together with the <hi>Defender</hi> of it: Religion it self suffers by the vile hypocrisie of those who pretended to an higher strain of godliness in practice, and reformation in Discipline, than yet the world had ever known. And it is likely to suffer an eternal reproach, as long as there are any <hi>Popish</hi> blasphemers, to cast it into the teeth of <hi>Protestants,</hi> that they never thought their Religion <hi>pure enough,</hi> till it was <hi>washt in the blood</hi> of a <hi>Christian King,</hi> of the same profession with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. O prodigy of wickedness! That ever <hi>Justice</hi> should be pretended to the committing of a Crime so full of dread
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:107038:23"/> and horrour, that it might well puzzle and <hi>nonplus Justice,</hi> how to <hi>punish</hi> it, and <hi>mercy</hi> how to <hi>forgive</hi> it. That ever the increase of true Piety, and the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the honour of Religion should be made a colour to the shedding the <hi>blood of a King,</hi> a <hi>Fact</hi> that gave <hi>Religion</hi> the most <hi>mortal wound</hi> that ever it received, since it was first planted in the world by <hi>the blood of our Saviour.</hi> And yet those Sacred Names, <hi>The purity of Worship, The reformation of Abuses, The honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, Law, and Justice, and the due Liberty of the subject,</hi> must be made a <hi>Stale</hi> by those men (who could not else have successfully acted such a <hi>devilish</hi> part, unless they appeared like <hi>Angels of Light</hi>) to promote an impiety whose di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect design, and natural consequence was to <hi>overthrow,</hi> and <hi>root them all out:</hi> and when they had cast out and slaughtred, not onely their <hi>Brethren,</hi> but their <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Father,</hi> set up their cry with those hypocrites in <hi>Isaiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 66.5</note>
               <hi>Now the Lord be glorified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as this Fact was <hi>in it self</hi> most <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious,</hi> so it was most <hi>fatal</hi> in all its <hi>Train of consequents.</hi> Nothing but <hi>ruins and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:107038:23"/> extortion, distraction, sacriledg, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice, the blood of many, and the tears of all, personal, domestick, and publick evils, rents and divisions at home, scorn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt abroad,</hi> have almost ever since fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed one upon the neck of another: and would to God they were so little, felt and known, as to need recounting. Nor indeed, was it fit, that so horrid a Crime should have any better <hi>Attendants.</hi> And truly how could it be otherwise, where <hi>Oppression</hi> and <hi>Violence</hi> were the onely <hi>legislative power,</hi> where <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> the two <hi>Extri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, were alwayes striving for the upper hand? Where ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>lives, liberties,</hi> and <hi>estates</hi> depended onely upon the <hi>rude vote of the sword?</hi> Our <hi>Law,</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon sence and security of the Nation; and every mans best and richest Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, were themselves <hi>outlawed</hi> by the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Interests of a few ambitious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> contents. Our Church r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt in pieces by <hi>schisme, errours, heresies, damnable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Devils,</hi> not onely <hi>publickly breach't</hi> but <hi>publickly patronized t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet some <hi>easie minds</hi> are ready to think those times happy, because of the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:107038:24"/>
               <hi>Liberty,</hi> or rather indeed the <hi>licenciousness of Religion.</hi> But was Religion indeed in so good a plight, when in a <hi>Juncto</hi> the necessity, and usefulness of the <hi>Ministry</hi> was put to the Question? when <hi>learning, Religion,</hi> and the holy and precious <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God,</hi> depended upon the <hi>rotten breath</hi> of a Company of men of <hi>rotten and corrupt minds,</hi> whose <hi>gain w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s their Godliness,</hi> and had nothing <hi>holy</hi> belonging to them, but what they got by <hi>Sacriledge?</hi> Was Religion in so good a plight when we daily feared an <hi>Interdict</hi> upon our pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Assemblies? When the <hi>Solemne Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> of God was <hi>interrupted</hi> and <hi>affronted</hi> by every one that had but <hi>Impudence</hi> and <hi>Enthusiasme</hi> enough to do it? Nay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Religion was vanish't into <hi>canting Phrases,</hi> into an empty and notional pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, and that very Profession dwindled away into innumerable <hi>Sects,</hi> and <hi>Schisms, Err<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rs, and Heresies;</hi> that certainly none can think it was in a <hi>Prosperous</hi> conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but those who think Religion then prospers, when it is not <hi>much,</hi> but <hi>mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</hi> These that <hi>tolerated</hi> every Sect, every <hi>opinion,</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to carry themselves, as if within a while they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:107038:24"/> would have <hi>excepted the true.</hi> For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, when once men in Power can <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> of <hi>false Doctrines,</hi> the next step is <hi>to imbrace them,</hi> the next <hi>to impose them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea the <hi>sickleness</hi> and <hi>instability</hi> of our <hi>Ʋsurped Governments,</hi> which might give us hope of relief, proved onely the <hi>fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent renewing</hi> of our misery: one power still succeeding another in the same design; all seeking to <hi>advance themselves</hi> upon the <hi>ruines of the publick.</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member an <hi>Apologue</hi> of an ulcerated man, who, when his friends would have driven away a swarm of flyes, that had been long sucking his sores; let them alone, saith he, these are pretty well <hi>sated;</hi> but if you drive them away, <hi>fresh ones</hi> will come, with <hi>fresh appetites,</hi> and more tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment me. So truly it fared with us in our <hi>tosses and change</hi> of Governments. When one <hi>swarm</hi> of our Governours had their greediness, &amp; avarice some what glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then were we consigned over unto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who <hi>eat</hi> the very <hi>flesh</hi> of these Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and <hi>drank their tears and bloud.</hi> Yea and what was both the <hi>reproach,</hi> and <hi>aggravation</hi> of our misery, those <hi>flyes</hi> were but the off-spring of <hi>dirt and dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hills.</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:107038:25"/> Our <hi>plague</hi> was like that of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the very <hi>dust of the Earth crawl'd upon us.</hi> The <hi>meanest</hi> of the people were our <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> and out of those <hi>brambles</hi> proceeded fire, that consumed the <hi>Cedars of Lebanon.</hi> And according to the <hi>Pedigree</hi> of our <hi>Princes,</hi> such were our <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Teachers.</hi> If any could but <hi>prate nonsence,</hi> and <hi>prove it by Blasphemy,</hi> this was a sufficient <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secration</hi> into the <hi>Office.</hi> This was enough to make him a most admired <hi>light,</hi> who indeed was but an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> leading the silly and deluded rout, through the bogs and precipices of <hi>Error, and Heresy,</hi> into <hi>perdition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the posture both of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> in those blessed times of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> which they so much boast of, and which were so highly advanced by those mens zealous indeavours, that they were grown quite <hi>out of reach,</hi> and almost <hi>out of sight:</hi> and had not God by a Miracle of Divine mercy interposed, within a while we should neither have had the face, nor the name of <hi>Religion,</hi> or <hi>Liberty</hi> left amongst us. But he infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated their Counsells, and defeated their designs; and when their was no visible
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:107038:25"/> power to break them, he dash't them in pieces one against the other, till they mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually brake themselves. <hi>So let all thine Enemies perish O Lord; but let the King rejoyce in God, and joy in thy strength; through the mercy of the most high, let him never be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now although it hath pleased Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God to break that yoake from off our neckes, and to set us free from that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression and violence, yet we ought not onely to detest, but bemoan, the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages and wickednesses that were then committed; and seek to God, that he would avert from us those Plagues and judgments, which the guilt, of a <hi>Part,</hi> may deservedly bring upon these <hi>whole</hi> Nations. For this is the unhapiness of being link't, though not in <hi>conspiracy,</hi> yet in <hi>National Society</hi> with evil doers; that although we first suffer <hi>from</hi> their sins, yet we may afterwards suffer <hi>for</hi> them. When but one <hi>Achan</hi> had sinn'd; and that not so heinously, as to make him either a Murderer, or a Regicide; God punisheth the whole Camp of <hi>Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> for it, and causeth them to flee, and fall before their Enemies. Joshua 7.11. <hi>Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:107038:26"/> hath sinned, for they have taken of the accursed thing, and have also stollen and dissembled.</hi> It was but the fact of one <hi>Private man,</hi> and yet God chargeth it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole people, <hi>Israel hath sinned, and they have taken.</hi> Such a malignant influence hath the very <hi>community</hi> with wicked men, though we have no <hi>communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> with their wickedness, to diffuse guilt and judgments upon a whole Nation. Believe it, <hi>Bloud</hi> is a <hi>loud</hi> and crying sin. The <hi>first</hi> that was ever spilt, was heard as farr as from <hi>Earth,</hi> to Heaven. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.10, <hi>The voice of thy Brothers bloud cryeth to me from the ground.</hi> And <hi>Revel.</hi> 6.10. <hi>The soules under the Altar cry with a loud voice, how long O Lord holy and true, dost thou not judge and avenge our blood on them which dwell on the Earth.</hi> And if the blood of <hi>private persons</hi> be so audible in Gods eares, how much more loud and vocal, is the blood of a slaughtered <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch!</hi> Especially, when the blood, and oppression, and ruines of so many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands as were involved in the direful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequences of that fatal day, <hi>joyn</hi> their voices with it, <hi>assault</hi> heaven, and <hi>cry aloud</hi> for vengeance. Let us then <hi>cry mightily</hi> to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:107038:26"/> God, that the <hi>voice</hi> of our <hi>Prayers,</hi> may be <hi>louder</hi> in his Eares, than the <hi>voice</hi> of our <hi>provocations:</hi> and let us by our <hi>Tears</hi> wash away that foule stain that lyes upon our profession; and beg of God, that he would powre out a plentiful effusion of the <hi>blood of Christ,</hi> to cleanse these Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the guilt of <hi>blood:</hi> for nothing less than the <hi>blood of God,</hi> which could <hi>expiate</hi> even for the shedding of <hi>it self,</hi> can <hi>expiate</hi> for shedding the <hi>blood</hi> of a <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>